Attention
customers change.
>> If you want to know all about Andy
Warhol, just look at the surface of my
paintings and films [music] and me. And
there I am. There's nothing behind it.
[music]
Andy Warhol, an artist who his entire
life provocatively asserted that he only
existed on the surface, that he was just
a personality devoid of history and
emot. emotions.
Hiding behind halftruths and genuine
lies, Andy Warhol chose to wear a mask
all his life.
>> Warhold's personality, he never gave
anything away. It's important to realize
that
he hid behind fakery. You had to force
the secret out of him. [music]
There is always an interplay between the
simplicity of a painting, an utterance
or an image and something far more
complex which you discover little by
little.
>> The whole world knows his famous
paintings of Campbell soup tins and the
multiple portraits of Marilyn Monroe.
His
face is his signature and it has made
him a star. He is one of the most famous
artists of the 20th century. [singing]
And yet very few people know the man
hidden behind the artist.
If we go back to the childhood of the
man then known as Andrew Wah, we
discover a complex being influenced by
family traditions, popular culture, and
religion.
I don't think it comes down to one piece
of art. If he wasn't religious, I just
think a greater part of the theme of his
art would [music] be different.
>> It's important to understand the
cultural practice of religion.
Warhol's true origins are to be found
there.
From these miscellaneous influences
which were so deeply rooted in him, he
fashioned a unique world, an artistic
[music] and philosophic world, but also
a cold one.
His work is disturbing in its simplicity
and it's in direct confrontation [music]
with the upheaval of his time.
Andre Warhola, Andy Warhol's father,
settled in Pittsburgh in 1912.
He was joined several years later by his
wife Julia, newly arrived from her
native Slovakia.
They came here to find work, lured by
the promise of this land of freedom.
Pittsburgh was the capital of the coal
and steel industry and its chimneys
formed an imposing industrial landscape.
[music]
This urban environment was frighteningly
modern. The city was constantly
expanding and became the symbol of a
country destined to build the new
century.
>> Pittsburgh was known for a very
industrial city. Uh steel was very big
here in Pittsburgh. steel mills, they
they run every day, 7 days a week, 52
weeks a year, [music] 365 days a year.
They don't shut down at all. And you can
see it's very visible. There's flames
coming [music] out. There's smoke.
>> Pittsburgh was a city of opposites. On
the one hand, you had the Fricks, the
melons, and the Cargis, the rich
families who built these American
cities, and on the other all the
workers.
Where Uncle Andy lived was mainly a lot
of immigrant workers who came over. So
that would be the poor side of the town.
>> But the crash in 1929 brought the
machines to a standstill and one by one
the factories closed down. The youngest
Woola, Andrew, was only one year old. So
his father Andre took any job he could
get
in the coal mines, in the steel works,
on building sites. He worked non-stop,
relentlessly.
Andre was a hard worker. He was off and
away from home. Uh and sometimes he
would even have to travel and he
wouldn't be home for days on end. But um
it was just his way. He was a
workaholic.
>> When he came home, he was exhausted, you
know, and and he would just go to sleep,
eat, go to sleep, and get up and do it
all over again. And it was mainly just,
you know, to support the family and to
survive. You know, my grandfather didn't
have hobbies. He didn't golf or he
didn't do any. His hobby was his family.
Andy's parents responded to poverty by
seeking solace in spirituality, by
observing their religious traditions.
Every Sunday, this little boy would
accompany his parents and his two big
brothers through the soulless streets of
the city. Come rain or snow, they walked
the 10 km to church.
the Byzantine Catholic Church of St.
John Chrissum.
>> My grandmother was very religious and
she required that everybody in the
family go to church and uh you know say
their prayers. Uh the religious uh you
know segment of Catholicism it's called
the Byzantine Catholic.
An inongruous island in the midst of a
sea of greyness, this church in
Pittsburgh was edged on little Andy's
imagination. [singing]
>> You walk into the church and you're
totally stimulated. [singing]
Your eyes are stimulated by all the
beautiful, wonderful icons,
>> by the gold screens, the dome, the
stained glass windows.
[singing]
>> There was a very beautiful Byzantine
Catholic root that the the parishioners
would sing and again very pleasing to
the ears as well as [music] the use of
incense.
It's based off of sort of the premise of
heaven on earth. So when you walk into
the church, you're surrounded by beauty
and this beautiful scent and this
beautiful chant. [singing]
>> Andy was fascinated by these pious
images. Opposite him above the altar was
a painting of Jesus and his disciples at
the last supper.
like to joke around where Uncle Andy was
maybe sitting in church as a little boy
and seeing maybe an icon of Jesus and
thinking, "Boy, that would really be
neat if we could put Marilyn or Shirley
Temple up there."
>> 30 years later, Andrew Warhol, who had
[music] become Andy Warhol, painted his
most famous painting, Gold Marilyn
Monroe, based on these religious [music]
icons.
>> [music]
>> In it, the actress is immortalized as a
saint on a gold background. Her [music]
features simplified by blocks of color.
In 1934, Andy's father, Andre, finally
found a permanent job. The Warhol's
situation improved, and they moved into
this house, a stone throw from their
church.
This house became a bubble for Andy,
protecting him from the outside world.
>> Andy was an odd child, very different
from his two older brothers who were
more robust and played football.
He was born with a delicate constitution
and was soon afflicted by a nervous
condition known as St. Vita's dance.
People suffering from this condition
cannot control their movements or
speech.
This illness kept him off school for
quite a long time. Tied to his mother's
apron strings, he was delighted and
spent his days drawing.
It was mostly Julia, my grandmother, who
took care of Andy, and she's the one
that was really instrumental in showing
him how to draw. I think that's where it
all started. You know, I always say that
she was probably his biggest [music]
influence because she had a very unique
artistic way about herself. She had this
magical quality. He would use a soup can
and use paperier-mâché to make flowers
and then she would sell those door todo.
She would go into more some of the more
richer neighborhoods.
>> She was musical, she was artistic, she
decorated eggs, she she uh did a lot of
uh sewing. So, uh I think her her talent
rubbed off on Andy in a big way.
>> [music]
>> Andrew Warhola was installed in the
center of the living room. He was
treated like a king, the privilege of
the seriously ill.
This illness kept him away from other
teenagers, stopped him going out with
friends, having his first sexual
encounters, his first love affairs.
[music] He was isolated from all that.
[music]
From a very early age, he got into the
habit of observing
His
[music]
childhood was one of hardship and
illness.
He was a sickly child.
He was teased at school.
He was a mommy's boy and privileged too.
His
mother molly coddled him and so he
suffered from terrible shyness which he
had to learn to overcome.
Warhol really was extremely secretive.
He wore a mask so that no one would know
who he was.
There was doubtless a link between this
decisive childhood episode and his
distant relationship with things.
>> It was as if he was looking at life
through a glass window.
>> [music]
>> Now listen, let's go over there and play
that big game I learned at Little Rock.
Come on, gather around.
>> 10, 20, 30, uh, 25.
>> Besides his home life, Andy only had one
form of escapism from the disturbing
reality, the cinema. In the 1930s,
Hollywood was experiencing a golden age.
As the economic crisis dragged on,
Americans hid on mass in darkened rooms.
By the age of seven, Andrew was a
regular cinema goer.
>> He was passionate about the cinema, but
that was normal in the 1930s when the
big studios were in their heyday.
He was fascinated by America's
sweetheart, Shirley Temple. He wrote her
a note and by some miracle he received a
reply from Shirley Temple which he
showed to everyone. He was jumping for
joy.
>> What did the
>> He was a true fan obsessed with this
little girl. This child star who had
been fashioned by the studios and
appeared in all the most popular films.
>> For the children of that generation, the
cinema provided a window onto the
outside world. In that sense, Hollywood
had the ability to fire up people's
imaginations in a way that we don't
really understand today.
[music]
Obviously, for any teenager in Andy's
position, the vision of another world
and of things he had never imagined
possible suddenly appearing on screen
was quite magical.
[music]
Andy's parents realized he would not
have the same future as his two brothers
who were already in work. Despite their
modest salaries, they managed, thanks to
a bery to enroll him in drawing classes.
>> Andre, he doesn't come from an elite
class. He's not very, you know, educated
in art, but he knew there was something
special about Uncle Andy. Um, and he
knew that, you know, that it was worth
to save as much money as he possibly
could to ensure that Uncle Andy would go
to college and even to go further and to
make that prediction that you're going
to be proud of Andy someday.
Andre didn't live to see his [music]
son's success. In 1942, he died
suddenly, poisoned by contaminated water
on [music] a building site.
And he was 14. Deeply affected [music]
and incapable of confronting his
father's death, he refused to go to the
funeral.
Three years later, he did [music] his
father proud and got into Carnegie Tech
University.
There he did courses in applied arts,
design, [music] and graphics.
But soon Andy was drawing attention
[music] to himself and caused his first
scandal with this painting
a self-portrait [music]
which he called the broad gave me a face
but I can pick my own nose.
His teachers were divided.
He was very close to getting thrown out.
But Andrew applied himself and in 1949
he finally [music] got his diploma.
Age 21. Despite being anxious about
leaving his mother, he realized that if
he wanted to live off his art, he had to
move. He headed for the new capital of
art and the avanguard, New York.
Thanks to steel from [music] Pittsburgh,
the city had the world's biggest
skyscrapers, such as the Empire State
Building.
Charlie Parker and Miles Davis played in
the city's jazz clubs
and Jackson Pollock with his abstract
expressionism ruled the contemporary art
world.
It was also the birthplace of beat
generation writers such as Jack Carowak
and William Burrows.
On Time Square, Andy stood outside
flashy cinema facads where the big stars
were on screen.
Marilyn Monroe, Elizabeth Taylor, and
Marlon Brando.
With only $200 in his pocket, Warhol
moved to Manhattan. He lived in a small
studio flat with a friend who was to
become a great painter, Philip Palstein.
York.
>> The two men experienced a brief period
of bohemianism while living as artists
in New York. They moved from flat share
to flat share in a downtown that was not
at all like it is today. All the
neighborhoods in lower Manhattan were
seedy, flea ridden, and full of
cockroaches. They were teeming with
young people trying their luck, but not
all of them would succeed.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Andy trolled around fashion magazine
editing houses with a cardboard box full
of drawings.
Everyone was instantly seduced by his
stylishness and boyish charm.
He seduced the female editors of Vogue
and Harper's Bazaar and other leading
fashion magazines such as Glamour, which
commissioned him to produce a series of
drawings. He had struck lucky.
I couldn't get a seat on our
>> As soon as he arrived, Andy got a
commission from Glamour magazine for a
series of articles entitled, "What is
success?"
>> He delivered sketches of rather
whimsical women.
>> His drawings caused a sensation and
advertising contracts followed. The
swankiest shops in New York called on
him to dress their windows.
It was around this time that he dropped
the last letter of his name and started
signing his work Andy Warhol, a much
more [music] American name.
He became a successful young graphic
designer.
Then one day out of the blue, his mother
Julia turned up at his apartment.
>> Stars Hollywood presents. She came in in
approximately 1952. It was 2 years after
he arrived in New York. She was
determined that she would take care of
Andy and live with him. And he was okay
with that. For the next almost 20 years,
she was there in New York um doing all
his housework and taking care of him at
home. And I think she was an important
um support for him all through those
years. Uh, and I think that they gave
him a kind of a security that that no
one else could give him.
>> In the mornings, Uncle Andy and and my
grandmother, who I affectionately
referred to as Bubba, um, Uncle Andy and
Bubba would kneel down and say a prayer
before he left. You say a prayer. It's a
dangerous world out there. And, you
know, you you ask for God's protection
so [music] that you could come home.
>> [music]
[music]
>> She had this really [music]
very interesting handwriting u which was
actually just the handwriting that
everybody [music] in the region where
she came from. They all learned this
type of handwriting. This was the
standard to people in New York. It was
[music] very odd and strange and kind of
fun and it didn't really fit anything
that they knew. It was just so foreign.
And all the art directors, they loved
this. The the all of his clients loved
it. And pretty soon she was doing entire
pieces under Warhol's name. and she
actually won two uh professional graphic
design awards in New York.
Throughout [music] the 50s, Andy
Warhol's work went handinhand with the
dawn of the consumer [music] society.
With a string of prizes to his name and
admired by his peers, [music] he was now
a rich man. Born poor to immigrant
parents, he had turned his life around.
[music]
In 1960, [music]
he bought this four-story house in the
city's poshest neighborhood, Upper East
Side, near Central Park.
As always, his [music] mother followed
him and moved into the ground floor.
Andy started painting. He had made his
fortune so he could afford to do his own
work and turned down advertising
commissions.
He was making work for himself,
trying out new things. At that time, his
nephews regularly made the trip from
Pittsburgh to see him. Some years later,
James Warhola, who had become an
illustrator, drew this comic strip based
on childhood memories and visits to see
his uncle and of his discovery of Andy
Warhol's very first works.
It was just a wonderful space uh for
kids. And a lot of our memories are when
we visit him in New York at this
townhouse. We remember when he was doing
his first soup cans, just doing these
simple images of soup cans. They almost
look like advertising art. They didn't
look like fine art, but he did them
well. So, he was hand painting all these
images. And uh we knew it took quite a
talent. And uh we loved watching him do
it. He would start working probably
around 10:00. He'd be busy all through
the day painting. Uh he would be
listening to music.
>> One point he he realized my brother and
I were really good workers. So he he put
us to work stretching canvases. So we
were thrilled to help him stretch
canvases at home. He was very uh exact
on how he like his canvases without any
wrinkles and we were able to do it. So
when I was seven and my brother was
nine, we were we were doing that kind of
work. That's when he was doing the the
paint by number paintings or the dance
step paintings, the dollar bills. Uh we
stretched all those early paintings. U
and uh it was pretty thrilling.
The paintings started piling up in the
small house.
Andy condensed all his influences in his
paintings.
They contained everything that had
shaped his lucid vision of the era. The
dollar sign and the Campbell soup can
were almost like religious icons of
everyday life.
My mother um she was very direct with my
uncle. I know that she didn't think uh
any of it was art. So, she didn't really
take it too seriously. And she'd tell
him and and I actually asked him why
didn't he get rid of all the stuff at
home that was kind of uh his art. And he
always told her it was really important
that someday it was going to be worth a
lot of money. That was one of my uncle's
kind of principles that that anything
could be art. It doesn't matter what
type of subject or what your medium is.
Anything could be art. I think that was
an important principle and I think
that's what he based his early pop art
paintings on.
>> In 1962, he discovered a printing
technique which allowed him to reproduce
his works at Infinitism on canvas.
Screen printing.
It was a provocative way of turning
creativity into production.
The traditional art world may have found
it shocking, but it opened doors in some
urbane and decadent circles.
That's when he met Emil de Antonio, an
artist agent famous for his intuition.
That marked a turning point in Warhol's
career as an artist.
Warhol had been working nonstop.
One day he presented two paintings to
Emil de Antonio who was famous in the
art world for being a consultant with a
nose for quality. Warhol showed him a
painting of a bottle of Coca-Cola
painted in an expressive lyrical style
with a lot of feeling. It contained
trickles and gestures. It was about
painting and paint.
Then he showed him another painting of a
bottle of Coca-Cola with no trickles and
no gestures. And Emil de Antonio said to
him, "That's it. You must plow that
furrow." That direct identification with
the model without commentary.
Pop art speaks for itself.
His suggestion was to set up a
production line to focus on quantity to
mass reproduce a single image.
What would it mean to be swamped by
images?
The more you look at something, the less
meaningful it becomes.
In 1962, the critics got carried away.
The Campbell soup can paintings were
even nicknamed the Mona Lisa of the
modern age. Warhol understood that pop
art was factual art, the art of the
present. His work made radical claims
that consumerism and showbiz were the
new religions of the 20th century.
To get rid of his mannered gestural
approach, he had to brainwash himself.
>> Got this on himself. I'd feel on safer
ground than yours. Whatever you say.
He basically had to distance himself
from his feelings and become a machine.
This was not a marketing project or a
pose. It was a real artistic objective
to invent a form.
[music]
>> At the end of 1962, American pop art was
born.
As proof of his meteoric rise to fame,
almost all of Warhol's works found
buyers at this [music] one-man show at
the Stable Gallery, one of the best
known galleries in New York.
Obsessed with the mass media, Warhol
compulsively read and collected all the
newspapers he could find.
On the 4th of June 1962, he came across
a front page [music] announcing the
death of 129 people in a plane crash.
With costic irony, he painted a huge
picture of it over 2 m square,
reappropriating the paper's morbid
images.
For Warhol, who had witnessed the
widescale expansion of the media, it was
clear that this exploitation of death
had something about it that was both
unbearable and crucial. This image was
revealing of a new form of society that
thought nothing of exploiting death in
this brutal way.
That was one of the salient features of
the world he now found himself in. Just
like Marilyn's ethereal beauty, the two
go hand in hand. Remember that he
decided to paint Marilyn on the day he
learned of her suicide.
[music]
>> NBC Radio News on the Hour brought to
you by the Metropolitan Life.
>> Celebrities, sudden deaths, car crashes,
racist attacks. Andy Warhol's art is
anything but inoffensive.
Painting is commemorative for Warhol. It
commemorates that which has disappeared
forever. It is a way of keeping and
preserving an image of what has been
lost. The posthos of these car crashes
is all the greater when the images show
people we don't know. They are images of
strangers, but they show the extent to
which images of dead people are a key
issue. Not just from a sociopilosophical
point of view, but also from an
aesthetic point of view.
>> This series shows the electric chair in
Singh prison.
It is an empty brutal throne,
the violent symbol of a society where
death and [music] chauis are
intertwined.
The house in Lexington had become too
small for Warhol. He needed work
assistance and he had to find somewhere
to store his mass productions.
Meeting Gerard Malanga was useful. He
was a student, a young poet [music] with
a flamboyant man of brown hair.
>> [music]
>> In January 1964, they invested in a
disused factory which they covered in
aluminium and [music] silver paint.
The mythical factory was born.
[music and singing]
[singing]
>> It was a factory. It was a hat factory.
But when we saw the the space, it was
empty. It was dark. It was,
>> you [music] know, gloomy. It was not a
very
enthusiastic space. But, uh, Andy saw
something, the possibilities. So, Andy
signed a lease [music] and then we moved
into this space.
>> It had a lift like the ones you used to
get in old lofts. The lift door opened
straight onto the loft. There was no
front door or anything.
[music]
[singing]
>> [singing]
>> Warhol had the factory.
>> He loved surrounding himself with crazy
people, people who took drugs and
crossdress.
>> Warhol really liked strange people. I
think he he liked people in general. I
think he was [music] he really studied,
you know, personalities and he liked
having a lot of different people. And it
was [music] this idea of like mixing
really amazing people from high society
and low society and maybe kind of
creating some friction, see what [music]
happens.
>> The factory was a place to hang out in
and meet people.
It was a place of spontaneous
experimentation. [music]
Very soon a modern hybrid lifestyle
developed there.
work, artificial paradises, and all
night parties all merged into one.
>> Andy Warhol created his own superstars
there. These men, women, and
transvestites were models and muses.
Fashioned in the image of the Hollywood
dream factory of his childhood.
>> The place acted as a magnet for
fashionable New Yorkers.
Andy Warhol always remained slightly
aloof.
He was both at the center of things and
in the background, a voyer.
People thought that everyone was hanging
around me at the factory, but it was the
opposite. I was hanging around them.
We didn't really know what was going on
at the factory. And at the same time, he
didn't really bring too many people home
from the factory. So, he kind of he
liked it that way, I think. because at
home he had his privacy,
a certain amount of peacefulness
and um and especially his mother who
took care of him. Uh I think that was
really important for him to grow as an
artist.
>> In 1965, out of the blue, Andy Warhol
announced that he was going to stop
painting and focus on film making.
I remember at that time in the mid60s
when he said he was giving up painting
and and it just didn't make sense that
he would give up painting when he became
so successful. But then he was doing
films and there again I don't think
anybody understood the films because
they were kind of artsy strange films.
New York was going not only New York but
also the the West Coast, San Francisco.
There were new movements in cinema to to
expand the forms of cinema from just
narrative storytelling Hollywood kind of
public cinema into poetic forms of
cinema and abstract forms of cinema.
Jonas Mikas, a pioneer of experimental
cinema, ran the only New York cinema
showing underground films.
The first series of films that Andy
brought to me were a a series of kisses.
He decided to project it not a normal
speed but slowed down. That was a genius
stroke really. If you project it 24
frames per second, it's a little bit
boring. Naturalistic,
but when you slow it down, you it
becomes like super reality. A little bit
of a dream is brought in unreality. What
was in the air at that time in all of
the arts was like art uh in time, but he
brought it to cinema. main contribution
was to go back to the origins of cinema
and to reinvent it. He was the lumiere
of uh of the 60s
>> using primitive film making techniques
with no editing. Warhol observed
day-to-day life. His films are like
pictures barely moving. His film making
was a continuation of his painting. At
that time, Anes Vada, the director of
Cleod Sankaset was also working on
temporality in films.
She was in New York and she had come to
the factory because she had plans to
work with one of Warhol's superstars,
Viva.
[music]
We were the little new wave when we came
to America. That's what we were known
as.
Andy was pleased to see us. He gave me a
warm welcome and spoke about this and
that. I told him I wanted to meet Viva
with a view to making a film with her.
Viva, you must work with her. She made a
wonderful film. Cleo from 5 to 7.
>> If I had made it, I would have shot from
5 to 7. He would have made it in 2
hours. It took me two months.
I loved that. Coming from France, we
stuck to traditions and did things by
the rule book. Especially in the 60s,
they were all moving away from
traditional perceptions and Warhol was a
wonderful pioneer for that.
>> His most radical film was Empire. It was
a static shot of the Empire State
Building shot in July 1964.
Screened in slow motion, the film lasted
eight hours with no shot changes.
>> People really hated his movies, the
early movies. When we showed Empire in
the movie theater, people were throwing
things at the screen. And Andy was
getting worried because we were standing
in the back of the theater. He said to
me, "Do you think they really hate it?"
Oh yeah, I think they do. [laughter]
He revolutionized film making simply by
taking on the issue of time and
continuity.
I mean it's important that someone did
that. It doesn't mean people are going
to rush to see his films at the cinema
but his films marked a turning point for
me in the history of film making. We
didn't look at time in the same way
after that. I think there was film
making before Andy Warhol and film
making after him.
Andy Warhol shot nearly 60 films over 5
years experimenting with film making on
the same industrial scale that he made
paintings.
He dreamt of running his own avanguard
studios and wanted to see his name
associated with a rock band.
In 1965 he went with Sherard Malanga to
a concert at Cafe Bazaar.
Velvet Underground were playing.
[music]
So we actually [music] went down to see
them perform and this was a matinea
like I don't know 3:00 in the afternoon
in this cafe in Greenwich Village. There
was no stage. It was just the same floor
and there were [music] tables with young
kids at the different tables. It wasn't
a an auditorium or anything.
>> [music]
>> And um I just happened to have a whip
with me as a fashion a coo just to tie
it on my belt. And um at some point I
took the whip off my belt and I started
dancing with the whip while they're
performing. Well, within 5 minutes
everybody at the tables got up off the
chairs and they started dancing too. No
one was dancing at the beginning.
Warhol was instantly seduced by their
raw and poetic style. It was a sort of
erotic, wild lament with crude lyrics.
Warhol offered Velvet the use of the
factory to rehearse in.
>> Nobody took it seriously. Nobody felt at
that time that it will be that
important. Actually, we thought that
Nico, she was just a very bad singer and
uh it was just part of that [music] of
life.
>> Lou Reed when he and Andy kind of
connected. I think that uh something
special happened. They were both
breaking new ground and I think that uh
it was exciting period to be there in
New York um doing what they were doing.
That was part of my uncle's concept of
of bringing it all together in in one
big um uh kind of artistic performance.
[music]
>> Velvet became part of the factory,
giving it a new more rock and
underground identity. Punk before its
time. It was a hysterical time with more
and more people turning up at the
factory. In 1968, the spirit of
provocation and impertinence gained
momentum. It was a violent and worrying
time in the history of America.
>> CBS News in New York with a special
report on Martin Luther King, the
aftermath.
>> The assassination of Martin Luther King
triggered riots in most of the big
cities.
>> Negro community is clearly angry, often
uncontrollably angry.
>> In the spring, the building housing the
silver factory was to be demolished.
They had to move out.
Warhol found the ideal place in this
building in the south of Manhattan. A
new factory which was to be the scene of
a tragic episode.
One of the weird and wonderful people
hanging out at the factory [music] was
Valerie Salanis.
She was openly gay and had just
published the Scum Manifesto, a [music]
radical feminist pamphlet.
>> [singing]
>> That Valerie was crazy. She belonged to
a group called Scum, Society for Cutting
Up Men.
>> One day, Valerie Salanis offered Andy a
film script.
>> The title was Up Your Ass.
>> He wasn't interested, and after a while,
he announced to her that he had lost the
script.
On the afternoon of the 3rd of June
1968, Valerie Salanis showed up at the
new [music] factory again.
>> She was waiting in the lobby and they
actually rode the elevator [music] up
together and
and he had a phone conversation with
Viva and I guess she was at at the
beauty salon having her hair done.
Salonist pulled out her her gun and shot
him
while he was on the phone.
Warhole was crouched [music] over like
this when the bullet hit him. And so it
it came through the side like this
instead of this way and it passed
through like [music] something like five
or six or seven organs.
It took a while for the ambulance to
come.
When he got to the hospital, he was very
near death. He had lost a lot of blood.
They operated for about 5 and 1/2 hours.
He after the surgery, he was laying in
his hospital room
>> and he thought that he had died because
he could hear on the television that
Kennedy had been shot.
>> Young Robert Kennedy first won fame.
>> He thought that that's what happened
when you die. You just relive history.
And uh he had no idea that that it was
Robert Kennedy who had been shot. This
this is what he claimed. Anyway,
>> my oldest brother Paul, who was studying
to be a priest, he stayed with my uncle
for a few months uh during that summer.
It was a really traumatic [music]
experience uh for everybody and for
especially my uncle because uh it took
him many months to recover [music] from
that.
>> He was discharged after 2 months of
convolescence. He'd come through it, but
he was [music] very weak. He said, "I'm
a survivor."
>> He said he felt as if he were living in
another world, a much more uncertain
world. He said he thought he was only
afraid of God, but that had all changed
now.
That photograph is incredible. It's a
record of what he went through. It also
shows his ability to rise above it.
Those are the stigmata of a man who
almost died. They are proof of what he
endured and of his resurrection.
>> It was a big turning point for his
career. I think his work had changed. I
think his personality changed a little.
I think it was just a natural way of him
shifting and being more careful. U but
creatively it was definitely a I think a
stepped on.
In the years that followed, Andy Warhol
was fearful [music] and his fear was
deeprooted.
He was so traumatized he made a clean
sweep. His former associates left the
factory. No more superstars, no more
marginalss.
By giving up this community which had
inspired him for all those years, he
lost his creativity.
For him, the 70s were empty years.
Perhaps that's what his work was dealing
with in the 70s. Emptiness.
In May 1969, Esquire's cover featured
Andy Warhol drowning in a tin of
Campbell's soup.
The headline was unambiguous. The final
decline and total collapse of the
American avanguard.
In 1970, Andy Warhol carried on creating
a void around him and [music] sent his
mother to Pittsburgh to live with his
brothers.
Julia died on the 22nd of November 1972.
As with 30 years previously on the death
of his father, Andy didn't go to the
funeral and didn't speak to anyone about
his mother's death.
[music]
A new factory was born out of his fears,
the office. Now neurotically obsessed
with death, he sought refuge in the
practice of compulsively recording
everything. His tape recorder and
Polaroid camera never left his side.
He changed, hiding behind his viewfinder
as a way of seeing without being seen,
of being present but not really there.
>> He blurred the high and low line. Uh he
was constantly criticized by the New
York art establishment for be going out
too much. His way of working was to be
out in the world to he was tape
recording everybody. He was I videotaped
all the time. He was taking Polaroids of
people documentation of his time and was
part of his art and what he wanted to
do.
>> Adi Warhol changed worlds and
environments. He was gradually moving
into the world of money.
>> This was something quite different.
These were businessmen. They carried
briefcases. He was no longer directing
films. He was interviewing people and
making television programs. There was a
complete change. 1971 is the beginning
of really doing portraits. Fred Hughes
is a business manager and close
confidant and Bruno Bishop Berger his
Swiss dealer really developed this idea
of doing portrait commissions which were
way making money and Andy understood the
art historical importance of that
because in the history of art the the
courts of Europe always had portraits
commissioned of the wealthy people of
the time the lords.
During the 70s, Warhol sold his talent.
McJagger, John Lennon, Grace Jones, and
numerous other stars commissioned
[music] portraits.
He produced between 50 and 100 of them a
year for astronomical sums. This work
was neither personal nor political. He
just turned them out.
These portraits came to overshadow his
return to darker and more intimate work.
In [music] 1976, Warhol made Skulls, a
screen printed series of 60 skulls.
As if returning from the dead, he seemed
to drop his mask and confront his
audience headon, revealing his mystical
obsessions for the first time.
In 1978, he produced the mysterious
shadows. [music]
These abstract shadows were reproduced
at Infinitum.
They gave us a glimpse of his obscure
hallucinatory dreams.
[music]
There is a possibility that he was
becoming more spiritual in his work and
a little more introverted like the
abstract paintings. The shadow paintings
really made the [music] art critics stop
in their tracks because they couldn't
they didn't know what to make of it.
They are so spiritual, so beautiful and
ethereal.
>> Warhol's late works are just as
extraordinary as his early works. They
are predigious, what with the shadows,
the camouflages, the diamonds, and the
piss paintings. They are just as
interesting as his early works. Like an
apple tree blossoming before it dies.
>> Andy Warhol seemed to sense the arrival
of his own death.
His works are now openly religious.
His
final work in 1987 was a variation on
Leonardo da Vinci's Last Supper.
>> He painted the Last Supper in 1986,
shortly before his death. Most [music]
Carpathian roos in their living room or
kitchen wherever they ate, they would
have that [music] some sort of picture
resemblance of the last supper to remind
them of that very [music] important
event. That was a part of his life that
he didn't talk much about. But I believe
at that point in his life, he really
needed to get it out. It was his way of
communicating. It wasn't like he was
going to stand on top of a a soap box
and say, "Hey, I'm religious." That was
his quiet way of saying look I am very
religious and this [music] is important
to me and I'm going to paint something
that's very close to my heart.
That's [snorts] the advantage of
success. It liberates you from a number
of constraints. He exploited that
success to do something he had wanted to
do for a long time. He could now pick up
the Christian theme again and use it as
a subject matter for his paintings. He
made explicit what was implicit in a
number of his paintings from the 60s.
>> On the 22nd of February 1987, Andy
Warhol died aged 58 of a heart attack
following a routine gallbladder
operation. [music] In New York, 2,000
people attended a mass to pay tribute to
him. The speeches made by the artists
nearest and dearest gave the public a
glimpse of just how religious he had
been.
>> We didn't learn until after his death he
would go to a homeless shelter in New
York and hang out with the homeless the
whole day. And he didn't even tell us.
It's probably not the image that most
people think of of Andy Warhol, but I
mean all the other stuff is there. You
know, this is just another side that
makes him that much more, you know,
intriguing and and special. But we never
talked about [music] personal things
very much and he didn't like to touch
upon those things. I knew he was going
to church because if you picked him up
on a Sunday from his home, he stopped at
the the church nearby go in. I would
wait outside. He'd go in for a few
minutes and come back out.
>> He didn't he didn't talk about these.
This is all private. I kind of missed
this uh this personal contact that I had
with him and he was always interested in
what I was doing and he'd tell me
something new that he was doing. Um and
uh you know he was always Uncle Andy to
us. So uh um